Guide to the John Pittman Papers TAM.188
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series III: Political Activities
  - Racism and Racial Discrimination, World Conference for Education of, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Racism - World Marxist Review- Symposium, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - The Railroad Workers Link, undated (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Real Estate Career, 1954-1958 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Record of Work Done - Time Copy, undated (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Republican Convention - By Richard Walker, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Rubin, Daniel - "On the Life of Henry Winston, National Chairman, C.P.U.S.A.", undated (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - San Francisco Workers School, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Soviet Discussion - Letter to the Editor ( People's World), undated (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Soviet Press Agency Translations, 1970-1978 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Soviet Union, Trip to - Notebook / Journal, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Speaking Engagements, undated (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - The Spokesman: Articles of Co-Partnership, etc., 1931, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - United Nations Correspondents Association (Application for Membership), 1953 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - United Nations Founding Conference - San Francisco, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Western Negro Statesman, undated (Box 3, Folder 55)
- Series IV. Writings
  This series is arranged alphabetically, and the bulk of it is from 1960-83. It comprises somewhat more than half of the collection and contains typescripts of radio speeches given on KSAN, journalism dispatches, newspaper column typescripts and clippings, press telegrams from Moscow, photocopies of his articles in Political Affairs, notebooks, typescripts for numerous unpublished and published articles and for several pamphlets and for papers given at conferences sponsored by World Marxist Review and other communist fora. Pittman's writings were largely concerned with the problems and struggles of African Americans and of people of color worldwide, the strategy and tactics of the communist movement, and with its relationship to the capitalist powers and the developing countries.
  - Africa Against the Axis, ca.1943 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Africa Calling: Isolate the Racists, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - "Aid to Africa" - Incomplete, undated (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - "American Communists" - Komsomolskaya Pravda, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - "American Motion Pictures - A Weapon of Imperialism", 1947 (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - "Banning Nuclear War Propaganda", 1984 (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - "Behind the Iron Curtain" - 4 Part Series ( The Daily Worker and People's World), 1946 (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - Book Reviews, 1973-1977 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - "Building the Communist Press", 1975 (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - "Capitalism USA, As Catholic Bishops See It", undated (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - "Capitalist Integration in the Western Hemisphere", undated (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - Colloquium - Julius Lips Institute, Karl Marx University, Berlin, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - "Color Blindness - A Ploy to Derail Affirmative Action" (for Black Liberation Journal), 1982 (Box 3, Folder 68)
  - "Combating Crisis Consequences", 1984 (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - "Combating Effects of the Worst Crisis", undated (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - "Coming Battle for a Military Détente", undated (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - "Communists by the Minute", 1950 (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - "Concerning Native Americans and Peoples from the Caribbean and Central American Areas", undated (Box 3, Folder 73)
  - Conferences and Symposia (held in the) USSR - Pittman typescripts, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 74)
  - Conferences and Symposia ( World Marxist Review) - Pittman typescripts, 1974-1979 (Box 3, Folder 75)
  - Conferences and Symposia, Miscellaneous ( WMR?) - Pittman typescripts, 1974-1976 (Box 3, Folder 76)
  - "The C.P.U.S.A. and U.S. Public Opinion", 1979 (Box 3, Folder 77)
  - "C.P.U.S.A: Origins and Sources of the C.P.U.S.A.", 1979 (Box 3, Folder 78)
  - "The C.P.U.S.A's 65 Year Fight for Peace", 1984 (Box 3, Folder 79)
  - Daily Review of Soviet Press, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 80)
  - "The Daily Worker and Freedom of the Press", 1952 (Box 3, Folder 81)
  - The Daily World, Content of - (For Party Affairs), undated (Box 3, Folder 82)
  - "The Daily World, In the Struggle for the Masses", 1974 (Box 3, Folder 83)
  - "Davis, Angela" - Untitled ts, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 84)
  - "DeGaulle and U.S., Mandate System, Wallace's View", 1944 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - "Economic Planning" (Note cards and ts), undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - "Equality for Afro-Americans: The Communist View" (Drafts), undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - "The Equality of Nations - Notes on", undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - "Existing Socialism: Its Meaning for the USA", 1979 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Fictional Writings Notebook, ca.1963 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - "Focus on Racism" - (3 ts), 1973 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - "For Peace, Jobs, and Equality", undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - "From Cradle of Bourgeois Freedom to State Monopoly Capitalism", undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Ganbatte- Book Review, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - German Communist Party Conference (Bonn), Reports from, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - "Government by the People" (60th Anniversary of Russian Revolution), 1973 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - "The Great October Revolution and the United States of America" (For the International Conference of World Marxist Review), 1977 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - "Grim Future for Native Americans", 1981 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - "How People's Democracies Emerged", 1985 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - "How Polish Government is Liquidating Bigotry", undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - "How Socialist States Help Africa and Why" ts - New Quarterly, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - "The Ideology of U.S. Messianism", undated (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - "Imperialism's Main War Party - Then and Now", undated (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - "An Impression of John Hope" (President, Morehouse College), undated (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - "Impressions of Socialist Korea", undated (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - "Inevitability of War in the Capitalist World", undated (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - "Information for Changing the World", 1981 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - "Inter-American Relations and the Export of Capital", undated (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - "Jewish-Negro Relations", undated (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Journalism Dispatches, 1940s (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Journalism Dispatches, 1942 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Journalism Dispatches ( Daily Worker), 1945 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Journalism Dispatches ( Daily Worker, People's World, Chicago Defender), 1946 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Journalism Dispatches ( Daily Worker, People's World, Chicago Defender), 1947 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Journalism Dispatches, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - "Ku Klux Klan" by John Badger (aka John Pittman), undated (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - "The Logic of a Life" ( Soviet Foreign Literature), 1961 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Lovejoy, E.P. - "N.S. Khrushchev's Visit Opens Way to a Significant Improvement in US - USSR Relations", 1959 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - "Mandate System and World Peace" (Germany/Africa), 1936 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - "Marxist - Leninist Party in the Soviet Union", 1976 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - "Marxist Philosophy", undated (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - "May Day Centenary", undated (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - "May First: Its Origin and Significance", 1978 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Miscellaneous Writings, undated (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - "Morehouse College Football Dope for 1925" (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - "Multi-National State Development", 1982 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - "Nate Shaw: Man of the Heroic Mold (An Anatomy of the Survivals of Slavery: a Damning Indictment of Racism)", 1976 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - "National Issues Before Congress Now in Session" - ( The Spokesman) By John Pierpont (aka John Pittman), 1937 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - "National Questions in the USA in the 1970s", 1979 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Newspaper Columns (Clippings and Typescripts) Most by Robert Badger, undated, 1942-1945 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Newspaper Columns- The Daily Worker(Clippings), 1950 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Newspaper Columns (Typescripts), undated, 1946-1947 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Newspaper Columns- The Daily Worker(Clippings) "Of Things to Come", 1949-1953 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Newspaper Columns (Typescripts and Clippings), 1970-1980 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Newspaper Columns (Typescripts and Clippings), 1981 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Newspaper Columns (Typescripts and Clippings), 1982-1983 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - North Korea, Trip to, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Notebooks (14), ca.1931, ca.1968-1970s (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Notebooks: International Conference on the October Revolution and the Contemporary Scene, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Notebooks on Race (4), undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - "Oriental Labor in California" (Bibliography), undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - "Party Theoretical Work: Basis of Political and Ideological Struggle", undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - "Peaceful Coexistence" Book Review, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - "Permanent Commissions of the Soviets", 1978 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Pittman, Margrit, Writings re: Soviet Union, 1959-1962 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Playwriting, Notes on, undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - "Point Four - New Name for the Old Imperialism", 1950 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Political Affairs- Articles (ts), 1973, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Political Affairs- articles (photocopies), 1958-1985 (Box 5, Folder 14A)
  - Political Affairs- Margrit Pittman articles (photocopies), 1968-1987 (Box 5, Folder 14B)
  - Press Telegrams from Moscow, undated (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Press Telegrams from Moscow, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Press Telegrams from Moscow, Jan 1960-Jun 1960 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Press Telegrams from Moscow, Jul 1960-Dec 1960 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Press Telegrams from Moscow, Jan 1961-Jun 1961 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Press Telegrams from Moscow, Jul 1961-Dec 1961 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Press Telegrams from Moscow, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - "Problem of the Subjective Lag", 1979 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - "Problems of an Unemployed American", ca.1961 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - "Proletarian Internationalism and the Revolutionary Process", undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - "Race and the Pacific", 1942 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - "Racism and War" (Parts I And II.), 1976 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - "Racism, Class Roots of", 1976 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - "Racism, Current Problems of the Struggle Against", undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - "Racism: The Death Sentence for/A Death Sentence for/Is Sentenced to Death", 1970s (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Radio Broadcasts: KSAN (San Francisco), 1941 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Radio Broadcasts: KSAN (San Francisco), 1942 (Box 6, Folder 8A)
  - "Readings from the Marxist - Leninist Classics", undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - "Red Heels", 1925 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - "A Report on the Soviet Theory and Practice of Peaceful Coexistence", undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - "Robeson and the Soviet People" ( New World Review), 1961 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - "The Rout of the Fascist Axis Bloc and the USA", 1985 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - "Scientific and Technological Progress and the Position of the Working Class in Capitalist Countries", 1986 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - "Similarities, Differences", 1979 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - "Sixty Years of the Soviet Multinational State" ( The New World Review), 1982 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - "Smog - How Socialism Deals with it", 1959 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - "Socialism and Communism - Theory and Practice", 1981 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - "Socialist Integration", 1979 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - "Socialist Poland's Heroic Example", 1986 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - "Some Aspects of the Life and Work of Karl Marx of Particular Significance to the People of the USA", 1978 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - "Some Features of the Present Stage of the General Crisis of Capitalism in the USA", 1975 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Soviet Agriculture, Corrections of Article on, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - "Soviet Armenia and the Forbidden Truth", 1961 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - "Soviet Foreign Policy", 1941 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - "Soviet Jazz: Another Challenge" ( Mainstream), 1961 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - The Soviet Path to Peace, undated (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - The Soviet Path to Peace- Two Reviews of (Hy Lumer and Irene Paull), undated (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - "The Struggle for Military Détente", 1977 (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - "The Struggle in the USA for the Second Front", 1975 (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - "Third World Non-Socialist Countries Winning Political Independence and Statehood During and After World War II" (List), undated (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - "Three Levels of Peace Activity in the USA", 1930s (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - "Towards a United, Independent, Sovereign Ireland", 1979 (Box 6, Folder 33)
  - "Trilateralism, US Imperialism's New Scenario", undated (Box 6, Folder 34)
  - "Two Paths for America", 1953 (Box 6, Folder 35)
  - "Two Systems Competition", 1974 (Box 6, Folder 36)
  - "The United Nations and the Struggle for Détente", 1974 (Box 6, Folder 37)
  - Unpublished Writings, undated, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 38)
  - Untitled Typescript - "The Going in France is Tough, but not so Tough as Goebbels…", ca.1944-1945 (Box 6, Folder 39)
  - Untitled Typescript - "Hard, Bitter Fighting Awaits our European Invasion Armies…", ca.1943-1944 (Box 6, Folder 40)
  - Untitled Typescript - "We Live in an Epoch of World Revolution…", ca.1930s (Box 6, Folder 41)
  - Untitled Writings, undated (Box 6, Folder 42)
  - "Upturn in US Labor's Internationalism", 1980s (Box 6, Folder 43)
  - "US Communists in the Struggle Against Unemployment", 1983 (Box 6, Folder 44)
  - "US Constitution: A Record of Unfulfilled Promises", ca.1987 (Box 6, Folder 45)
  - "USSR, An Introduction to Socialist Democracy in the", 1977 (Box 6, Folder 46)
  - "US Supreme Court and American Working Class Movement", 1931 (Box 6, Folder 47)
  - "US Workers and Latin America", 1980s (Box 6, Folder 48)
  - "US Worker's Struggle", 1985 (Box 6, Folder 49)
  - "US Youth and the Nuclear War Threat", 1985 (Box 6, Folder 50)
  - "Victory and National Liberation", 1975 (Box 6, Folder 51)
  - "Victory and National Liberation: An Addendum" ( New World Review), 1975 (Box 6, Folder 52)
  - "The Victory of Poland's Trade Unions", 1986 (Box 6, Folder 53)
  - "Victory the Hard Way", 1942 (Box 6, Folder 54)
  - "The View from Soviet Estonia" ( Mainstream), 1961 (Box 6, Folder 55)
  - "Watergate and After", 1974 (Box 6, Folder 56)
  - "Watergate and Détente", undated (Box 6, Folder 57)
  - "What is America to Me?", undated (Box 6, Folder 58)
  - "What the CIA, FBI Exposés Disclose", undated (Box 6, Folder 59)
  - "Why New Economic and Information Orders?", 1985 (Box 6, Folder 60)
  - World Marxist Review/ Prague - Misc. Pittman Typescripts, 1975-1979 (Box 6, Folder 61)
  - "World Politics and Global Problems", undated (Box 6, Folder 62)
  - "The World This Week - GOP Platform, China's Celebration, South African Trends", 1944 (Box 6, Folder 63)
  - "World War II" [re: National Question, Colonial Issues], ca.1942-1944 (Box 6, Folder 64)
  - "A Year Long Emergency for the CPUSA", 1984 (Box 6, Folder 65)
  - "Zionism, The True Face of", 1976 (Box 6, Folder 66)
- Series V. Photographs, Graphics, Realia, ca.1890s, 1960s-1970s; 1960-1975
  These visual materials and artifacts (arranged alphabetically by folder title) mostly relate to John Pittman's friends, family, professional work and travels. Most of the materials in it are photographs (mainly black and white), unless otherwise indicated. Among the photographic portraits of Pittman and his relatives and friends are a late nineteenth/early twentieth century group photograph that includes his mother, Carrie Badger Pittman, and an early twentieth-century portrait of a man with a close resemblance to Pittman, who may be Pittman's father. Images shot in the Soviet Union (including Pittman at Red Square in front of Lenin's tomb with other dignitaries, and commercial photographs of various tourist spots in Moscow at night, such as the Kremlin lit by floodlights) and in Prague were probably shot at the same time as John and Margrit Pittman's stint as Moscow correspondents for the People's World and John Pittman's time on the editorial board of World Marxist Review. On the other hand, the small number of images from Mexico (shot by People's World photographer Elmer Allen) do not seem to have come from any journey that Pittman himself took; similarly there are a handful of photographic images of various persons with whom (with the likely exception of Angela Davis) Pittman was not personally acquainted, ranging from Lyndon Baines Johnson to an image of Le Quang Vinh (leader of the independent Hòa Hảo army of Vietnam that fought against the Viet Minh and who was imprisoned and executed by the government of South Vietnam). Graphics and realia include a small print of a New Masses logo, and plates and mat molds for the title and accompanying photograph of Pittman for his weekly column in the People's World, "The World This Week."
  - Graphics - Communist Campaign Poster from Great Britain, ca 1960s (Box Shared Tamiment A006, Folder 1)
  - Graphics - Print (lithograph?) and Newspaper Clipping, ca 1930s-1940s (Box Shared Tamiment A006, Folder 2)
  - Mexico - Fishers and Peasants, 1963 (Box Shared Tamiment A006, Folder 3)
  - Portraits – John Pittman, ca 1960s-1970s (Box Shared Tamiment A006, Folder 4)
  - Portraits and Snapshots - John Pittman's Friends and Relatives, ca 1880s-1970s (Box Shared Tamiment A006, Folder 5)
  - Portraits of Others - United States President Lyndon Baines Johnson, Karl Marx, Le Quang Vinh (Vietnamese prisoner), Angela Davis, ca 1870s, 1960s-1970s (Box Shared Tamiment A006, Folder 6)
  - Realia: Printing Plates and Mat Molds, ca 1920s-1930s (Box Shared Tamiment A006, Folder 7)
  - Soviet Union - Moscow, ca 1959-1961 (Box Shared Tamiment A006, Folder 8)
  - Unidentified – Group of People Posed in front of a Monument (statue of a soldier), Location Unknown (probably in Eastern Europe), ca 1960s (Box Shared Tamiment A006, Folder 9)
  - Unidentified - Meeting in Prague; meeting in unidentified location (probably Eastern Europe), ca 1970s - 1987 (Box Shared Tamiment A006, Folder 10)